All
right. בוקר טוב, Boker tov, apologies for those of you looking for
us online. Our video did not work, but we're here in עבודה
זרה. Avodah Zarah. We're hopefully going to be in פרק ח. Perek
Chet. We are picking up from the middle of דף ז עמוד
ב. Daf Zayin amud Bet. The משנה Mishnah was asking about exactly
when around the holidays of the idolaters are we allowed or
forbidden to engage in business with them. Rabbi Yishmael said three days
before and three days after, and we saw that there was a
discussion in the גמרא: Gemara:
does it include the day or is it just the day before
or just the day after? If you think about it, which is
interesting, if the day, and they have some of that discussion, I'm
going to move on, is Sunday and we're looking at, and it's
a question of what exactly is that Sunday, but we're looking at
three days before and three days after
and
the day itself, what that means is that for seven days we
can't do business and basically every week is the same thing. So
it's kind of a nice way of saying don't ever do business
with them. As we saw yesterday, there was some discussion about what
exactly are the parameters of this and then we brought an opinion
of נחום המדי. Nachum HaMadi. And because we brought an opinion by
נחום המדי, Nachum HaMadi, we are going to bring a few other
opinions by him and we will see that the Rabbis say about
all his opinions this statement נשתכח הדבר ולא נאמר. Nishtaka hadavar velo
ne'emar.
And we are in the גופא, Gufa, which is in the first
line of the wide lines. נחום
המדי אומר אינו אסור אלא יום אחד
לפני אידיהן. Nachum
HaMadi omer eino assur ela yom echad lifne ihen.
This is נחום המדי's Nachum HaMadi opinion, and who is he? Did
we talk about him yesterday? I'll see that. נחום המדי Nachum HaMadi
is a תנא Tanna from the first century, so just before the
destruction of the Temple, and hopefully we'll get to somebody else right
from that same era.
Presumably his name המדי HaMadi indicates that he comes from מדי. Madai.
He's a foreigner and therefore he has slightly different opinions about how
to live with the non-Jews. But the Rabbis' opinions about all his
statements, we'll try to go through them not too slowly, is נשתכח
הדבר ולא נאמר. Nishtaka hadavar velo ne'emar.
It's two options: either, no, this is like hearsay, it was never
said before, or it was said but only in the בית מדרש
Beit Midrash for discussion and then was lost. Okay, והאיכא רבנן בתראי
דקיימי כוותיה? Veha'ika rabanan batrei dekaimi kavatei? So like, afterwards,
aren't the Rabbis holding with the same opinion? גמרא's Gemara asking, מאן
חכמים נחום המדי הוא. Man chachamim? Nachum HaMadi hu. So again, since
we're talking about him, we're going to go and see a few
other statements that he made and were rejected. תניא אידך: Tanya idach:
נחום המדי אומר מוכרין להם סוס זכר וזקן במלחמה. Nachum HaMadi omer
mocherin lahem sus zachar vezaken bamilchama. אמרו לו נשתכח הדבר ולא נאמר.
Amru lo nishtaka hadavar velo ne'emar. So נחום המדי's Nachum HaMadi opinion
was that he, you can sell the non-Jews
a male old horse during the war there.
And they said no, נשתכח הדבר ולא נאמר. Nishtaka hadavar velo ne'emar.
Now interestingly, and if I'm lucky enough we'll do this together next
Tuesday, this relates to a משנה Mishnah that's going to come in
דף יד עמוד ב. Daf yud daled amud bet.
And there's going to be a statement, we can look at it
briefly if you want to flip to that place.
The משנה Mishnah in יד ב Yud Daled Bet in the bottom
says: מקום שנהגו למכור בהמה דקה לעובדי כוכבים מוכרין מקום שנהגו שלא
למכור אין מוכרין ובכל מקום אין מוכרין להם בהמה גסה עגלים וסייחים
שלמים ושבורים. Makom shenahagu limkor behema daka le'ovdei kochavim mocherin, makom shenahagu
shelo limkor ein mocherin, uvechol makom ein mocherin lahem behema gassa agalim
usiyachim shelemim u-shevurim. רבי יהודה מתיר בשבורה ובן בתירה מתיר בסוס. Rabbi
Yehuda matir bishvura u-ven patera matir besus.
Okay, so we're talking about what kind of animals can be sold
to the idolaters, to the עובדי כוכבים? Ovdei kochavim? A place that
is customary to sell, sell; not customary, don't sell. And בהמה גסה,
Behema gassa, big animal, in any case not
עגלים. Agalim. Calves and baby horses, whether they're wounded or broken, Rabbi
Yehuda says broken, wounded is okay, and Ben Beteira allows horses because
horses are considered a different category and we're not quite going in
there, we're just looking at what נחום המדי Nachum Hamadi says. So
נחום המדי Nachum Hamadi said we're selling a male old horse in
war.
And the Rabbis said, eh, no. And then they challenge: ואיכא בן
בתירא דקאי כוותיה, דתנינא בן בתירא מתיר בסוס. ve-ika Ben Beteira de-ka'ei
ke-vateih, de-taneinan Ben Beteira matir besus. Ben Beteira allows us to sell
horses. Objection: בן בתירא לא מפליג בין זכרים לנקבות, איהו מדי קא
מפליג בין זכרים לנקבות,
Ben Beteira lo maflig bein zecharim linekevot,
ihu mi-da-ka maflig bein zecharim linekevot, is only נחום המדי. Nachum Hamadi.
דרבנן סבירא ליה ולרבנן נשתקע הדבר ולא נאמר. de-rabbanan sevira leh, u-le-rabbanan
nishtaka hadavar velo ne'emar. So this is something we don't hold by,
and
there's a whole thing about the horse, I'm not going into this
now, we will hopefully do this next year.
מדינת ישראל Medinat Yisrael sells lots of arms to non-Jews.
Yes, so the horses were a weapon. Yeah. Yes, so therefore they're
going into a different category, they're not like a work animal and
all that. Okay. And also interestingly,
מדרבנן, mi-de-rabbanan, you're not allowed to ride a horse on שבת Shabbat
because you might break a branch in order to hasten the horse
to go, but not from דאורייתא, de-oraita, yes.
And it's surprising it's not דאורייתא de-oraita because there's a פסוק pasuk
that you would think would be דאורייתא. de-oraita.
Next thing. תניא, Tanya, נחום המדי Nachum Hamadi אומר: omer: השבת מתעשר
זרע וירק וזירים. ha-shevet mit'aser zera ve-yerek ve-zirim.
So the שבת, shevet, which is a kind of a weed, possibly
some sort of a dill or maybe anise, not sure, possibly dill.
רש"י Rashi says dill. Dill. It gets tithed in the seed, the
leaves, and the stems. אמרו לו, נשתקע הדבר ולא נאמר. amru lo,
nishtaka hadavar velo ne'emar. No. Okay, so what is the issue with
the מעשר? ma'aser? First,
מעשר ma'aser of vegetables is מדרבנן, mi-de-rabbanan, דאורייתא de-oraita we only have
דגן תירוש ויצהר. dagan tirosh ve-yitzhar.
And second, you only have to be מעשר me'aser things that you're
going to eat. And then the question is, do you eat all
these pieces? Do you eat the זרע, עלים וגבעול? zera, alim ve-givol?
The Rabbis said נשתקע הדבר ולא נאמר. nishtaka hadavar velo ne'emar. ואיכא
רבי אליעזר דקאי כוותיה. ve-ika Rabbi Eliezer de-ka'ei ke-vateih.
So Rabbi Eliezer said the same, right? דתנינא רבי אליעזר אומר השבת
מתעשרת זרע וירק וזירים.
de-taneinan Rabbi Eliezer omer ha-shevet
mit'aseret zera ve-yerek ve-zirim. התם בדגנוניתא. hatam be-dignunita.
So the answer is that נחום המדי Nachum Hamadi said about a
wild plant, and that wild plant is not going to get tithed,
while Rabbi Eliezer said garden variety that is going to get tithed.
Okay. So now comes another person into our conversation. אמר ליה רב
אחא בר מניומי לאביי, amar leh Rav Acha bar Manyumi le-Abaye, and
he is also from מדי, Madai, he's from the same place that
נחום המדי Nachum Hamadi is. גברא רבא אתא מאתרין, כל מילתא דאמר
אמריתו ליה נשתקע הדבר ולא נאמר? gavra rabba ata mi-atrin, kol milta
de-amar amritun leh nishtaka hadavar velo ne'emar? A great guy has come
from our place.
Everything he said, you say stand back, this is go away. אמר:
איכא חדא דעבדינן כוותיה. amar: ika chada de-avdinan ke-vateih.
There is one thing we're doing as what he said. דתניא נחום
המדי אומר: שואל אדם צרכיו בשומע תפילה. de-tanya Nachum Hamadi omer: sho'el
adam tzorachav be-shomei'a tefillah. We have a מסורת masoret from נחום המדי
Nachum Hamadi who said a person asks for his request, for his
needs, during the שומע תפילה, shomei'a tefillah, during the middle of the
עמידה. Amidah. אמר: מר מיניה דהא דתליא באשלי רברבי. amar: mar min
de-ha'i de-talya be-ashlei ravrevei.
And רב אחא בר מניומי Rav Acha bar Manyumi said, this just
like leave of it, leave this הלכה halakhah because this הלכה halakhah
is hanging on big ropes or big trees, i.e., there's greater people
before him that said it, so let's not take it from him,
take it from other people. And now we're going to have a
discussion between Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Yehoshua about when it is okay
to share our personal request, needs, etc., during
official or structured תפילה. tefillah. דתניא רבי אליעזר אומר: שואל אדם צרכיו
ואחר כך יתפלל, שנאמר
de-tanya Rabbi Eliezer omer: sho'el
adam tzorachav ve-achar kach yitpallel, shene'emar in תהלים Tehillim we find a
פסוק pasuk that says: תפילה לעני כי יעטוף ולפני ה' ישפוך שיחו.
tefillah le-ani ki ya'atof ve-lifnei Hashem
yishpoch sicho.
We know from יצחק Yitzhak אין שיחה אלא תפילה שנאמר ויצא יצחק
לשוח בשדה. ein sichah ela tefillah shene'emar vayeitzei Yitzhak lasuach basadeh.
So this is when יצחק Yitzhak meets רבקה, Rivkah, the פסוק pasuk
tells us that he goes to... Eliezer says first a person should
say what bothers him and then like take that off his mind
and then settle himself for prayer.
But אבל רבי יהושע אומר יתפלל, aval Rabbi Yehoshua omer yitpallel, i.e.
שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, ואחר כך ישאל צרכיו. v'achar kach yish'al tzorachav.
And he brings another פסוק pasuk from תהילים: Tehillim: אשפוך לפניו שיחי,
Eshpoch lefanav sichi,
again looking at this שיחה, sicha, the תפילה, tefilla, the meditation, צרתי
לפניו אגיד. Tzarati lefanav aggid.
I will pour my heart, so i.e. I will say my תפילה,
tefilla, my שיחה, sicha, and then I will ask for my needs.
ורבי אליעזר נמי הכתיב אשפוך לפניו שיחי, v'Rabbi Eliezer nami haktiv eshpoch
lefanav sichi, so how do they still hold to their own opinion
but explain each other's פסוקים? pesukim? הכי קאמר אשפוך לפניו שיחי בזמן
שצרתי לפניו אגיד.
Hachi ka-amar eshpoch lefanav sichi bizman she-tzarati
lefanav aggid.
So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer can say I will pour my
תפילה tefilla after I say my צרות, tzoros, my צרתי. tzarati. ורבי
יהושע נמי הכתיב תפילה לעני כי יעטוף, v'Rabbi Yehoshua nami haktiv tefilla
l'oni ki ya'atof, how is he going to explain it? הכי
קאמר אימתי תפילה לעני בזמן שלפני ה׳ ישפוך שיחו,
Hachi ka-amar eimatai tefilla l'oni bizman she-lifnei
Hashem yishpoch sicho,
i.e. first say תפילה tefilla and then go into personal saying. מכדי
קראי לא כמר דייקי ולא כמר דייקי במאי מפלגי? Michtei kra'ei lo
kemar daikei v'lo kemar daikei b'mai miflagai? Like if each one can
take the פסוק pasuk of the other and explain their opinion, then
what exactly is the מחלוקת? machlokes? כידדרש רב שמלאי לעולם יסדר אדם
שבחו של מקום ואחר כך יתפלל מנלן?
Kide-darash Rav Simlai l'olam yesader adam shivcho shel makom v'achar
kach yitpallel menalan? רב
שמלאי
Rav
Simlai says a person should praise or organize
the praise that he has in front of השם Hashem and then
say his personal things. And we see it in the order of
the עמידה, Amida, right? First we say God of our father, God
is mighty, God is all the good things, and then we ask
for דעת, da'at, סליחה, selicha, רפואה, refuah, מחל, mechal, and all that.
מנלן? Menalan? Where do we learn this from? ממשה רבנו. mi-Moshe Rabbeinu.
דכתיב: de-chtiv: ה׳ אלוהים אתה החילות להראות את עבדך Hashem Elokim ata
hachilota l'harot et avdecha etc. etc., and this is when משה Moshe
starts his reiteration in the beginning of דברים. Devarim. And first he
says to God how great He is on heaven and earth that
can do all their great works and then he says אעברה נא
ואראה את הארץ הטובה. evra na v'ere et ha-aretz ha-tova.
Please let me cross over the desert, Jordan, whatever they need to
cross and see the beautiful land. So we learn from משה: Moshe:
first praise השם, Hashem, then ask whatever it is you want to
ask. We're at the top of ח׳ א׳. chet aleph. רבי יהושע
סבר ילפינן ממשה ורבי אליעזר סבר לא ילפינן ממשה. Rabbi Yehoshua savar
yalfinan mi-Moshe v'Rabbi Eliezer savar lo yalfinan mi-Moshe. רבי
יהושע
Rabbi
Yehoshua says that's what we do and we learn it from משה.
Moshe. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says no way. שאני משה דרב גבוריה,
Shani Moshe de-rav gevurei, and you can see רש״י Rashi at the
top there: גדולה מעשיו וחכמתו רבה רבה ונאה לו לשבח ולהדיף בשבחו
של מלך מלכי המלכים. gedola ma'asav v'chochmato raba raba v'na'eh lo leshabeach
l'hadif bishivcho shel melech malchei hamelachim. אבל איניש בעלמא נחזי כיוהרא. Aval
inish b'alma necheze k'yohara. Like
okay great, משה Moshe can do it, משה Moshe is a great
guy, משה Moshe is close to השם, Hashem, but just us? It's
very presumptive that we can actually think about ourselves that we are
focused on God's greatness when we have trouble. Right, like a child
doesn't come to their parents and say: Oh mom, you're so great,
can I have a candy? No, I want what I want right
now and okay. וחכמים אומרים לא כדברי זה ולא כדברי זה אלא
שואל אדם צרכיו בשומע תפילה. v'chachamim omrim lo k'divrei zeh v'lo k'divrei
zeh ela sho'el adam tzorachav b'shomei'a tefilla. And the חכמים Chachamim say
we have a spot for you where you can ask for your
own needs. This is in the ברכה beracha of שומע תפילה. Shomei'a
Tefilla. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה שואל אדם צרכיו בשומע תפילה.
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel halacha sho'el adam tzorachav b'shomei'a tefilla. Here
is our הלכה, halacha, this is where we can insert our things.
אמר רב
יהודה
בריה דרב שמואל בר שילת משמיה דרב אף על פי שאמרו שואל
אדם צרכיו בשומע תפילה אבל אם בא לומר בסוף כל ברכה וברכה
מעין כל ברכה וברכה אומר.
Amar Rav Yehuda beriah de-Rav Shmuel bar Shilat mishmei de-Rav: af al
pi she-amru sho'el adam tzorachav b'shomei'a tefilla, aval im ba lomar
b'sof kol beracha u-veracha me'ein kol beracha u-veracha omer.
If he remembers, and we know it from our סידור, siddur, if
a person... remembers to pray for somebody's health during the blessing of
health or פרנסה, Parnassah, then he can do a personal thing that's
relevant to that ברכה Beracha inside the ברכה. Beracha. אמר רב חייא
בר אשי אמר רב Amar Rav Chiya bar Ashi amar Rav אף
על פי שאמרו af al pi she'amru שואל אדם צרכיו בשומע תפילה
sho'el adam tzorachav beShomea Tefillah אם יש לו חולה בתוך ביתו im
yesh lo choleh betoch beito אומר בברכת חולים omer bevirkat cholim ואם
צריך לפרנסה ve'im tzarich leparnassah אומר בברכת השנים omer bevirkat hashanim as
we explained. אמר רב יהושע בן לוי Amar Rav Yehoshua ben Levi
אף על פי שאמרו af al pi she'amru שואל אדם צרכיו בשומע
תפילה sho'el adam tzorachav beShomea Tefillah אבל אם בא לומר אחר תפילתו
aval im ba lomar achar tefillato אפילו כסדר יום הכיפורים afilu keseder
Yom HaKippurim אומר. omer. And I'm sorry, I love this, that he
says, "Sure, we taught that a person can ask for his needs
during the ברכה Beracha of שומע תפילה, Shomea Tefillah, but if he
wants to speak his personal requests, if they're longer, even if they're
longer as long as the confession of יום כיפור Yom Kippur or
as the prayer of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, he can recite them
after." And something that I find very strong that in our tradition,
both in the תורה Torah and the תנ״ך Tanakh and still through
the rabbis, there was an element of us having to have a
personal conversation with השם Hashem and not just the written one, and
a lot of this slowly got
whatever, we got more towards the book and less towards our personal,
I think we're missing that piece, you know, that personal התבודדות. hitbodedut.
Yeah, for sure.
I was under the impression that you could actually hit any place
in the שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, even though these spots maybe more
appropriate, but that you could add anywhere within the שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh
Esrei.
This last statement was after, so is that how do we resolve...?
This last one, אם בא לומר אחר תפילתו אפילו כסדר יום הכיפורים
אומר im ba lomar achar tefillato afilu keseder Yom HaKippurim omer if
he wants. Our traditional is בשומע תפילה beShomea Tefillah and in the
appropriate thing. I find רבי יהושע בן לוי׳ס Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi's
opinion interesting. But even if you had like a, I think our
tradition, official tradition is in the ברכות berachot of the עמידה Amidah
where it is appropriate.
Right, I'm just asking in addition, do we hold that you can
actually include your personal prayer
wherever you wish in the שמונה עשרה?
Shmoneh Esrei? Yeah, wherever in the spots. Just in those spots.
No, but what I'm saying is you can't just do ברוך אתה
השם Baruch Atah Hashem okay let me just, you know, you can't
do it in the middle of a, you know what I mean?
Right. No one does anything in the first three
ברכות berachot anyway, and in terms of the last three, you do
it right before יהיו לרצון אמרי פי. Yihyu leratzon imrei pi. There's
certain places in שומע תפילה Shomea Tefillah you insert things or certain
things in רפאנו Refaeinu you add things or certain things in ברכת
השנים Birkat HaShanim you can add things.
As for the other ones, I mean, typically,
we're not adding anything, but I think you actually can towards the
end.
Like even in between the ברכות? berachot?
Yeah, in between the ברכות. berachot. But what I'm saying is you
can't say like תקע בשופר גדול Teka beShofar Gadol oh God
da-da-da-da-da, right? You gotta, I think you gotta do it more intentionally.
There's this tension between following the structure, right, and having a personal
relationship.
And I
think a lot of the structure
has kind of overcome us having a personal and that's a tough
one.
Okay, but on the other hand, following the
structure, that's a whole different שיעור, shiur,
provides more...
Yes, of course. You're like, "Oh my god, I completely forgot I
should pray for somebody's health," or blah blah blah. Yes, now we're
adding "rain in season", yes, like there's places where to insert it.
And how, I mean, I cannot produce prayer texts that are anything
like חז״ל Chazal created.
It's a whole different conversation of like, I think there's like a
language, we lost the language of how to. All right.
In the history of how the prayers developed, you see, I'm starting
to
wiggle a little bit,
you see how there were other approaches where there were additional prayers
added by the person who was saying the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei
if I recall correctly.
In a very minutiae metaphor or parable, you know, you go with
your kid somewhere and you say, "Say thank you," and the kids
say, I don't know, whatever, חס וחלילה chas vechalila the kid burps
or something as an appreciation of how tasty it was. Mom will
say, "No, that's not how you say thank you," right? In our
society, we say blah blah blah. Yes, yes.
Yeah, for what it's worth, other religions have this issue too. It's
a big dispute in Christianity
of
ordained prayers versus only personal prayers.
On the line of us and other religions, and what's similar and
what's different. So now we had a conversation about the days before
and the days after, and now we have specifically which holidays are
we talking about? Okay.
ואלו הן של עובדי כוכבים.
Ve'eilu hen shel
ovdei kochavim.
Oh, ש״ס Shas says גוים Goyim
rather than עובדי כוכבים. ovdei kochavim.
Yeah, ours is also. Yeah, ArtScroll pointed that out with the whole,
yeah, everything there instead of עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim used to be
גויים.
Goyim. Yeah, it used to be עובדי כוכבים. ovdei kochavim. ואלו אידיהן
של עובדי כוכבים, Ve-elu ideihen shel ovdei kochavim, I can only deal
with my text as it says, but there's a lot of other
instead of גויים. Goyim. קלנדא, Kalenda, וסטרנורא, Vesternura, וקרטיסים, Vekartisim, ויום
גנוסיא
של מלכיהם,
Veyom Genosya
shel
malkeichem, ויום הלידה ויום המיתה, Veyom haleida veyom hamita, דברי רבי מאיר.
Divrei Rabbi Meir. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, כל מיתה שיש בה שריפה...
kol mita sheyesh bah sereifa...
Is Kalenda like from calendar?
It is the same root.
It's
New Year's Day according to Steinzaltz.
Right, that's because calendar, right, like you change the year in the
calendar.
And throughout Europe in a weird number of countries that you'd think
were unrelated linguistically, they have a word for around there that comes
from that root.
This, also וסטרנורא, Saturnura, I don't know, like star? Saturn. Saturn, right.
But I don't know what the next one is.
וקרטיסים, Vekartisim, they'll talk about it, we'll get a little further. Okay.
וחכמים אומרים. Vachachamim omrim.
New Year's Day is also a Catholic holiday in the United States
as well. Most Catholics don't know that, but it's an obligation.
We're going to find out how little we can do on these
days, so let's not apply it to anything.
We have a lot of visitors on New Year's Eve, absolutely אסור
assur for more
than one reason.
כל מיתה
שיש בה
שריפה יש בה עבודת כוכבים ושאין בה שריפה אין בה עבודת כוכבים,
Kol mita sheyesh bah
sereifa yesh bah avodat kochavim veshein bah sereifa ein bah avodat kochavim,
אבל יום תגלחת זקנו ובלוריתו, aval yom tiglachat zekano uvelorito, ויום שעלה
בו מן הים, veyom she'ala bo min hayam, ויום שיצא מבית האסורין,
veyom sheyatza mibeit ha'asurin, ועובד כוכבים שעשה משתה לבנו, ve'oved kochavim she'asa
mishte livno, אינו אסור אלא אותו היום ואותו האיש בלבד. eino assur
ela oto hayom ve'oto ha'ish bilvad. So we
have holidays that are everybody's
holidays, and then we have holidays that are private. So the קלנדא
Kalenda and וסטרנורא Saturnura and וקרטיסים Vekartisim and the יום גנוסיא, yom
genosya, the
crowning of the kings and the deaths, all these are public. The
deaths depends if there was a burning of all the idolatrous stuff
or not. But then there's also personal days. יום תגלחת זקנו ובלוריתו,
Yom tiglachat zekano uvelorito, day that the person, a person maybe, I
don't know, somebody has a personal relationship with that person, we'll see
how this applies, but whatever,
I don't have any person names, but okay, פלוני אלמוני, Ploni Almoni,
that is his day that he goes shaving. So think about it
in those days you didn't just walk down the street to whatever
Supercuts and had a haircut but that was a day of celebration.
יום שעלה בו מן הים, Yom she'ala bo min hayam, coming back
from a journey. יצא מבית האסורין, Yatza mibeit ha'asurin, also interesting if
he was imprisoned for any reason, the fact that it's here means
that this is maybe not so uncommon, these things happen. ועובד כוכבים
שעשה משתה לבנו, Ve'oved kochavim she'asa mishte livno,
I'm going to stay with the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim that has
a celebration for his son, maybe it's his son's wedding or some
other great event. אינו אסור אלא אותו היום ואותו האיש בלבד. Eino
assur ela oto hayom ve'oto ha'ish bilvad. So that's a day that
we are instructed to stay away from just this day, just this
person.
Alright, let's learn a little bit about these חגים. chaggim. Okay, we're
not allowed to call them חגים, chaggim, but these days. Also, I
missed being here in the beginning but איד Eid in
the
Mishnah, my text at least is with אלף, Aleph, but in Arabic,
Eid is a holiday, it's a חג, chag, so it's a language
travel. גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב חנן בר רבא,
Amar Rav Chanan
bar Rava, קלנדא ח' ימים אחר תקופה, Kalenda cheit yamim achar tekufa,
וסטרנורא ח' ימים לפני תקופה, Saturnura cheit yamim lifnei tekufa, וסימנך, vesimanch,
and we have a פסוק pasuk from תהילים Tehillim in order to
explain us these things, אחור וקדם צרתני achor vakedem tzartani etcetera. תנו
רבנן, Tanu Rabanan, what do we talk about תקופה? tekufa? This is
the short days or the days of טבת, Tevet, right? So now
we're in the middle of the winter, right? Winter solstice. Eight days
before and eight days after. This also deserves like a whole lengthy
session because if you think about the coincidence of us having... if
the winter solstice is
December 21st, 22nd, 20th...
the
astrology
cuts in that time, right? Okay, we know somebody that has a
holiday that starts on the 24th in the evening and continues for
eight days. I'm just saying.
But not December 24th.
Not December, but
it becomes all kinds of times. But you say you think it's
related?
I'm sure it's related.
They having a holiday
that starts the night of the 25th.
This sounds like
yeah.
Anyway, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabanan, where is this from? לפי שראה אדם
הראשון יום שמתמעט והולך אמר אוי לי שמא בשביל שסרחתי עולם חשוך
בעדי וחוזר לתוהו ובוהו וזו היא מיתה שנקנסה עלי מן השמים. Lefi
she-ra'ah Adam ha-Rishon yom she-mitma'et ve-holech amar oy li shema bishvil she-sarachti
olam chasuch ba'adi ve-chozer le-tohu va-vohu ve-zo hi mitah she-niknesah alai min
ha-shamayim. אדם הראשון, Adam ha-Rishon, what he sees, every day gets shorter
and shorter and shorter and shorter. He's like whoa whoa what's going
on? The world is getting darker and and becoming again תהו ובהו,
tohu va-vohu, right, goes to chaos and disorder. That's the death that
I was punished with from heaven. עמד וישב שמונה ימים בתענית ויש
אומרים בתפילה. Amad ve-yashav shmonah yamim be-ta'anit ve-yesh omrim be-tfilah.
So now he's
sitting eight days, right, and fast and mourning and prayer, hoping to
reverse that verdict. Lo and behold, כיוון שראה תקופת טבת וראה יום
שמאריך והולך אמר מנהגו של עולם הוא.
Kevan she-ra'ah tkufat Tevet ve-ra'ah yom she-ma'arich ve-holech amar minhago
shel olam hu. All of a sudden he sees the days are
getting longer and longer. He said this is the custom of the
world. הלך ועשה שמונה ימים טובים לשנה אחרת עשאן לאלו ולאלו ימים
טובים. Halach ve-asah shmonah yamim tovim le-shanah acheret asaan le-elu ve-le-elu yamim
tovim. So now he decided, every year I'm going to do שמונה
ימים טובים shmonah yamim tovim and we have that expression in our
tradition. Look at the next idiom, וקבעם, uk-va-am, וקבעום uk-va-um we have
two, לשם שמים והם קבעום לשם עבודת כוכבים. leshem shamayim ve-hem k-va-um
leshem avodat kochavim. So he initially made it for the sake of
heaven, but the עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim took the same holiday and
made it for עבודת כוכבים. avodat kochavim. רגע, Rega, challenge.
Now we have two opinions, when was Adam created?
Possibly in תשרי. Tishrei. But what if he was created in ניסן?
Nisan? If he was created in ניסן, Nisan, he saw a different
calendar. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Of course, we always
have to hold by two opposite opinions simultaneously. Okay, בשלמא למאן דאמר
בתשרי נברא עולם יומי זוטא חזא יומי אריכי אכתי לא חזא. Bishlama
le-man de-amar be-Tishrei nivra olam yomei zuta chaza yomei arichi achti lo
chaza. All right.
The person that said that in תשרי Tishrei the world was created,
he indeed saw
short days, days shrinking, but he did not see days lengthening. So
for him, that is a challenge. אלא למאן דאמר בניסן נברא עולם
הא חזא ליומי זוטא ויומי אריכי. Ela le-man de-amar be-Nisan nivra olam
ha chaza le-yomei zuta ve-yomei arichi. The one that says that the
world was created in ניסן, Nisan, he saw days that are short
but days that are lengthening, days that are shrinking, like he saw
some pattern. דהא זוטיה כולי האי לא חזא. De-ha zutye kulei hai
lo chaza. This kind of shortness, this kind of darkness, he didn't
see. Also very interesting, it's obvious that we're in the northern hemisphere,
right? We're not talking about anybody that lives not where we live.
Okay.
Another view on this. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabanan. יום שנברא בו אדם
הראשון כיוון ששקעה עליו חמה אמר אוי לי שבשביל שסרחתי עולם חשוך
בעדי ויחזור עולם לתוהו ובוהו וזו היא מיתה שנקנסה עלי מן השמים
והיה יושב בתענית ובוכה כל הלילה וחוה בוכה כנגדו.
Yom she-nivra bo Adam ha-Rishon kevan she-shak'ah alav chamah amar oy li
she-bishvil she-sarachti olam chasuch ba'adi ve-yachzor olam le-tohu va-vohu ve-zo hi mitah
she-niknesah alai min
ha-shamayim ve-hayah yoshev be-ta'anit ve-vocheh kol ha-laylah ve-Chavah vochah kenegdo.
On that first day that Adam was created, when the sun set,
he said, oh no, the world's going back to darkness and תהו
ובהו tohu va-vohu and this is the death that was
sentenced on me from heaven and he was crying all day and
חוה Chavah was crying against him. I just want to point out
that I love it, but there's also tons of problems that we
don't have time to get into because what is that day?
When was חוה? Chavah? חוה Chavah as opposed to the woman? If
the first day that they were created is Friday and now it's
שבת, Shabbat, are they sitting in תענית ta'anit on שבת? Shabbat? Is
it the first day that they're not in the garden? Where is
the rest of the story? Okay, so like
questions, but metaphorically and this is the side that I can relate
to Adam, as soon as it's darkness, it's probably my fault, the
voice side of Adam, I did something wrong and therefore it's now
raining outside.
כיוון שעלה עמוד
השחר אמר מנהגו של עולם הוא.
Kevan she-alah
amud
ha-shachar amar minhago shel olam hu.
Because the sun rose, he said this is the custom, this is
how the world is נוהג, noheg, is behaving. עמד והקריב שור שקרניו
קודמין לפרסותיו שנאמר ותיטב להשם משור פר מקרין מפריס. Amad ve-hikriv shor
she-karnav kodmin le-parsav she-ne'emar ve-titav la-Shem mi-shor par makrin mafris.
He gave as a sacrifice an ox that its
horns preceded its hooves and we will just leave it alone
with other מדרשים midrashim that we don't quite understand, though we have
a פסוק pasuk from תהלים, Tehillim, how nice, in order to prove
it. One of the things we can explain is that when in
the the animals that were created in the week of creation were
created whole. not like a birth, right? They did not come out
one part at a time, so the שור shor was created from
the head, from its horns to its hooves. But what exactly it
means is קצת ktzat beyond us. ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל שור
שהקריב אדם הראשון קרן אחת הייתה לו במצחו שנאמר ותיטב להשם משור
פר מקרין מפריס. Ve'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel shor shehikriv Adam Harishon
keren achat hayta lo bemitzcho shene'emar vetitav la'Hashem mishor par makrin mafris.
So
one of the teachings, it's like a magical animal, right? Like a
unicorn that has just one horn per גמרא. Gemara. And then the
question מקרין תרתי משמע? makrin tarti mashma? Maybe מקרין makrin is in
plural and therefore there should be two? אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק
מקרן כתיב. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak mikeren ktiv. It's written in
כתיב חסר. ktiv chaser. Our tradition is מקרין makrin but it's written
without the י. yud. Alright, next challenge. אמר רב מתנה רומי שעשתה
קלנדא וכל העיירות הסמוכות לה משתעבדות לה אותן העיירות אסורות או מותרות?
Amar Rav Matna Romi
she'asta kalanda vechol ha'ayarot hasmuchot la mishta'avdot la otan ha'ayarot asurot o
mutarot?
If there is the festival of קלנדא Kalanda that Rome establishes and
there's all these towns mixed to it that are serving Rome, are
these towns permitted or forbidden in business for us? They are not
celebrating the idolatrous holiday, but they are serving Rome, who is, which
is. So what do we do with it? רבי יהושע בן לוי
אמר קלנדא אסורה לכל היא רבי יוחנן אמר אין אסורה אלא לעובדיה
בלבד. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi amar kalanda asura lechol hi Rabbi Yochanan
amar ein asura ela le'ovdeha bilvad. So רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi says anyone that comes even near to it, no.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says only the people that worship the holiday.
תנא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן אף על פי שאמרו רומי עשתה קלנדא וכל
העיירות הסמוכות לה משתעבדות לה היא עצמה אינה אסורה אלא לעובדיה בלבד.
Tana kvatei deRabbi Yochanan af al pi she'amru Romi
asta kalanda vechol ha'ayarot hasmuchot la mishta'avdot la hi atzma eina asura
ela le'ovdeha bilvad. Our
how we act is in accordance with the opinion of רבי יוחנן.
Rabbi Yochanan.
Even though Rome has the holiday of קלנדא Kalanda and all the
nearby towns, the business is only forbidden with the worshippers of the
holiday. And I think and again way beyond the time we have,
what are the different opinions that we hear, how many of them
lived actually like נחום המדי? Nachum HaMadi? He lives in חוץ לארץ.
Chutz La'aretz. So which level of interaction they actually have so that
some things are impractical? If we say the day itself, three days
before and three days after, and we think that every יום ראשון
Yom Rishon is such a day, we just said we can never
do business with anybody. So we see that there are different opinions
that try to work with it so that we're not completely disconnected.
Yes, Charles?
רב נחום המדי Rav Nachum HaMadi was from
מדי, Madai, which was Persian. Yes. So then you have a question
whether the Persian religion is really an idolatrous religion, which they often
write here.
And whether whatever is this יום ראשון, Yom Rishon, if it's Sunday
the way we understand it, right? Every Sunday go to church, or
if it's some other some other יום ראשון. Yom Rishon.
Yes.
Every day should be a דף daf day and we should study
this all day long, but since we don't, then we can't. Okay.
רמב"ם Rambam says you have to work for a living. That's that
really frustrates. I know.
I know. Strange, I don't know, almost idolatrous. Okay. סטרנליא וכרטיסים ויום
גנוסיא של מלכיהם ויום שהובלך בו מלך לפניו אסור אחריו מותר ועובד
כוכבים שעשה בו משתה לבנו אין אסור אלא אותו היום ואותו האיש.
Saturnalia veChartisim veyom gennusia shel malkehem veyom shehuvalach bo melech
lefanav asur acharav mutar ve'oved kochavim she'asa bo mishte livno ein asur
ela oto hayom ve'oto ha'ish. So two holidays of סטרנליא Saturnalia וכרטיסים
veChartisim and the day that is a festival of the king and
the day that the king was crowned. Before is forbidden, but afterwards
is permitted. And then we have specificity that will help us with
exclusions for the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim that has a party to
his son is only forbidden that day and that person. Okay. אמר
רב אשי אף אנן נמי תנינא דקתני יום תגלחת זקנו ובלוריתו ויום
שעלה בו מן הים ויום שיצא בו מבית האסורין אין אסור אלא
אותו היום בלבד
ואותו האיש. Amar Rav Ashi af anan nami tanina de'katani yom tiglachat
zakano u-vlorito veyom she'ala bo min hayam veyom sheyatza bo mibeit ha'asurin
ein asur ela oto hayom bilvad
ve'oto ha'ish.
This is our משנה, Mishna, right? As we have taught the day
shaving and hair doing and the day coming up from the sea.
see finishing a sea trip and the day that a person comes
out of prison, is, if it's a celebration to an idolater, only
that day and that person is forbidden.
You know we have two of those, we also say special prayer,
we add into the four cases from תהלים Tehillim where we say
a special prayer, you know of thanks for returning from a sea
voyage or...
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes,
yeah.
I mean we have four things on the same list.
Four, right,
and just
saying
two
of these are are parallel. בשלמא Bishlama אותו היום oto hayom לאפוקי
לפניו ולאחריו, leapuke lefanav ule'acharav, אלא ella אותו האיש oto haish לאפוקי
מאי? leapuke mai? Okay, so what is this משנה mishnah helping us
with? When it says only that day and that person,
when we say only that day, it
excludes days before
and after, so that like makes sense. But when it says this
person, what does it exclude that helps us with other teachings in
this issue? לאו לאפוקי משעבדיו? lav leapuke mishabdav? שמע מינה. shema mina.
So, oh, by saying only this person that is associated with this
celebration, we excluded the people that work for that person, we can
still engage with them because it's not their holidays, it's just their
job to help somebody else celebrate. Okay. תניא, Tanya, רבי ישמעאל אומר,
Rabbi Yishmael omer, ישראל שבחוץ לארץ Yisrael shebechutz la'aretz עובדי עבודת כוכבים
בטהרה הן. ovdei avodat kochavim betahara hen. Getting closer. Israel, Jews that
are abroad—this is a big question, where is abroad? For sure America,
sorry—they are worshipping idolatries בטהרה, betahara, בטעות. beta'ut. It's like just through
being here, there are opportunities to engage in idolatrous behavior בטעות. beta'ut.
כיצד? keitzad? Look,
you would think they'd bring on New Year's Eve, right, and all
that, but like those are obvious things. Look at the example: עובד
כוכבים oved kochavim שעשה משתה לבנו she'asa mishteh livno וזימן כל היהודים
שבעירו. vezimen kol hayehudim shebe'iro. An
idolater that made a party for his son—wedding or some other celebration—and
invited all the Jews in the city, אף על פי שאוכלין משלהן
ושותין משלהן ושמש משלהן עומד לפניהם, af al pi she'ochlin mishelahen veshotin
mishelahen veshamesh mishelahen omed lifnehem, מעלה עליו הכתוב ma'aleh alav hakatuv כאילו
אכלו זבחי מתים, ke'ilu achlu zivchei meitim, שנאמר: shene'emar: וקרא לך ואכלת
מזבחו. vekara lecha ve'achalta mizivcho. Okay,
even if they eat their own food and drink their own drinks
and they have their own server standing before them, still we bring
a פסוק pasuk from שמות Shemot that says it's as if they
ate from idolatrous offerings, because the פסוק pasuk says וקרא לך ואכלת
מזבחו. vekara lecha ve'achalta mizivcho. How? How do we get this from
this פסוק? pasuk? So we'll see what they do with the פסוק.
pasuk. The פסוק pasuk should have said ואכלת מזבחו. ve'achalta mizivcho. It
would have been enough to just say you ate from the sacrifice
and we could have maybe had more leeway. But because it says
וקרא לך, vekara lecha,
they
call upon you, we mean from it
that from the moment
you were invited into this gathering, you're already part of it. ואימא
עד דאכיל? ve'eima ad de'achil? In the text now, we could have
said only it's about the food and since they brought their own
food it's fine. מה רבא, ma rava, אם כן, im ken, נימא
קרא nima kra ואכלת מזבחו, ve'achalta mizivcho, מאי mai וקרא לך? vekara
lecha? משעת קריאה. mishe'at kriya. Why the added words on this extra
פסוק pasuk from Exodus, וקרא לך? vekara lecha? From the time they
call you, they invite you in. We're at the top of ח'
עמוד ב'. chet amud bet. הילכך, hilkach, כל תלתין יומין, kol tlatin
yomin, בין אמר לו מחמת הילולא ובין לא אמר לו מחמת הילולא,
bein amar lo machamat hilula uvein lo amar lo machamat hilula,
אסור. assur. Oh, 30, sorry, 30, 30 days between the
celebration, like let's say a wedding celebration, before or after, whether the
person, the idolater said, 'Oh, come on over, שבע ברכות, sheva brachot,
right? It's the 30 ברכות,' brachot, so
the person can say, 'Come on over, we're celebrating,' but even if
he didn't say and you know that there was a celebration, all
the meals before and after are considered thankfulness to their gods and
therefore אסור. assur. מכאן ואילך. mikan va'eilach. אי אמר
ליה מחמת הילולא אסור, אי לא אמר ליה מחמת הילולא, מחמת הילולא
שרי.
i amar lei machamat hilula assur, i lo amar lei machamat
hilula, machamat hilula sharei. So after the thirty days, if the idolater
says, "Come on over, I have some leftovers and we can re-celebrate
and it's now two months after," אסור, assur, but if he doesn't
say
and you're just invited over, מותר. mutar. וכי אמר לו מחמת הילולא
עד אימת? v'chi amar lo machamat hilula ad eimat? Okay, so what
if he did say this was due to a celebration, to a
wedding, and we can think of a lot of other celebrations? How
far, how long is this, until when is the celebration assumed to
be connected with idol worship and forbid? אמר רב פפא: amar Rav
Papa: עד תריסר ירחי שתא, ad treisar yarchei shata, until twelve months
of the year have passed since that wedding. ומעיקרא מאימת אסור? u'meikara
meimat assur? אמר רב פפא משמיה דרבא:
amar Rav Papa
mishmei d'Rava: מכי רמו שערי בסינא. michi rammu sharei b'sina.
And what about before? When is it
prohibited
before the wedding? רב פפא Rav Papa says in the name of
רבא: Rava: from the day that they cast barley into these dishes
or whatever to prepare for the wedding. There's two opinions whether they
prepare beer, they prepare alcohol for the wedding and begin this process,
or whether it's some like plant that is going to be used
as garlands or something else for the wedding. A hand? No hand?
Okay. ולבתר תריסר ירחי שתא שרי? u'lebatar treisar yarchei shata sharei? And
after twelve months of the year is that now
allowed? והא רב יצחק בריה דרב משריא איקלע לבי ההוא עובד כוכבים
לבתר תריסר ירחי שתא. veha Rav Yitzchak brei d'Rav Mesharsheya iqla l'bei
hahu oved kochavim l'batar treisar yarchei shata.
רב יצחק, Rav Yitzchak, the son of רב משריא, Rav Mesharsheya, happened
to be at a house of a certain idolater after twelve months
had already
passed. ושמעיה דאודי. u'shmaya d'odei. He heard him still being thankful,
giving thanks to his idol for his son's wedding. ופרש ולא אכל.
u'perash v'lo achal. He removed himself from the feast, withdrew from the
feast and didn't eat.
שאני רב יצחק בריה דרב משריא דאדם חשוב הוא. shani Rav Yitzchak
brei d'Rav Mesharsheya d'adam chashuv hu. Gemara tells us, and this is
very gentle how our relationship with our neighbors, like if we forbid
ourselves everything, we can't have any connection, and if we have too
much connection, we're going to get lost, right?
We're still going on eating kosher food, right?
We still take, yes, we're bringing our own,
right, being airline,
airline meals, aluminum foil wrapped and all that, OU aluminum foil. I
don't want to make any mistakes about that. All right. רב יצחק,
Rav Yitzchak, son of רב משריא, Rav Mesharsheya, is different. He was
an important אדם חשוב הוא. adam chashuv hu. He was an important
person and therefore his presence had an added value. And we have
these conversations all the time whether we, someone going somewhere, gives credence,
you say? Like, yeah, yeah, yeah, gives like weight
to this event and whatever. I just had the situation, going into
some event Friday night that's not Shabbosy. So now, in my role
in the shul, can I go to such an event? Can the
shul have a table in such an event? How do we, you
know, give weight to certain things? Here it's obviously not between us
and ourselves, but between us and non-Jews. Everybody will learn something else
from it. וכרטיסים, v'cartisim, back picking up from the Mishnah at the
third
top from ח' עמוד ב'. Chet amud bet. מאי כרטיסים? mai cartisim?
What is כרטיסים? cartisim? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל: amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel: יום שתפסה בו רומי מלכות. yom shetafsa bo Romi malchut.
It's the day that Rome became the ruling empire. והתניא כרטיסים ויום
שתפסה בו רומי מלכות? vehatanya cartisim v'yom shetafsa bo Romi malchut? We
have a teaching that there is כרטיסים, cartisim, there is that day
and a day that Rome became the empire. אמר רב יוסף: amar
Rav Yosef: שתי תפיסות תפסה רומי, אחת בימי קליופטרה מלכתא, ואחת שתפסה
בימי יוונים.
shtei tfisot tafsa Romi, achat b'imei
Kleopatra malkata, v'achat shetafsa b'imei yevanim. So we're really looking at two
days that the Romans became the empire. One is the war against
the south and one is the wars with the Greeks. According to
my watch I have five more minutes? Yes, yeah.
I don't want to get into, yeah, okay, okay, okay.
וכי
אתא רב דימי
אמר תלתין ותרין קרבי עבדו רומאי בהדי יונאי ולא יכלו להו. Vechi
Ata Rav Dimi Amar Tlatin
Vetarin Kravi Avdu Romai Bahadei Yavanai Velo Yaklu Lehu. The Romans had
and this is like again all these דפים dappim need so much
more unpacking what exactly what exactly
are
we talking about. 32 battles had the Romans against the Greeks and
were not successful עד דשותפינהו לישראל בהדייהו ad deshatfinhu LeYisrael bahadeihu until
they struck a partnership with the
Jewish people. והכי אתנו בהדייהו vehachi atnu bahadeihu
and this is the partnership that they created. אם מינן מלכי מינייכו
אפרכי אם מינייכו מלכי מינן אפרכי.
im minan
malkei minaichu aprachi im minaichu malkei minan aprachi. This is the partnership
we're going to do, said the Romans to the Jews or the
Jews to the Romans, but one way or another, this is our
opinion that again and think about the
practical entrance of Rome into the scene and and the metaphorical which
we'll see more of in just a minute and that's why I'm
slightly rushing but keep going yes
okay. So what they say this is how it's going to go.
If there's a king from us, say the Romans, we are going
to provide the Jews are going to provide the governors like the
local establishment and if we have the king, you will have the
local governors.
ושלחו להו רומאי ליוונאי עד
השתא עבדנא בקרבא.
veshalchu lehu Roma'ei leYavana'ei ad
hashta avadna bekarba.
Until now the Romans send a message to the Greeks and said
until now we tried to resolve our issues through battles. השתא נעביד
בדינא. hashta na'avid bedina. Now
let us do it through judgment.
So now they're like negotiating. Okay. The Romans are going to send
things to the Greeks to through the Greeks to figure out what's
going on. מרגלית ואבן טובה. margalit ve'even tovah. I'm going to send
a pearl and a precious stone. איזו מהן יעשה בסיס לחברו. eizo
mehen ya'aseh basis lachavero.
Which one should be the base and which one should be sitting
on top of the other one. I.E. the one sitting on top
is the better one, right, because you don't put a pearl in
the bottom of a even if it's a precious stone that would
be on top. Okay. They said, sorry, the so they send שלחו
להו מרגלית לאבן טובה. shalchu lehu margalit le'even tovah. Okay. Then they
send the Greeks send a response the pearl. The מרגלית margalit is
on top.
אבן טובה ואינך איזו מהן יעשה בסיס לחברו. even tovah ve'inach eizo
mehen ya'aseh basis lachavero. They send a precious stone and אינך inach
maybe onyx but like another
better okay better precious stone. Which one of them would be base
to the other? איזו מהן יעשה בסיס לחברו? eizo mehen ya'aseh basis
lachavero? אבן טובה לאינך. even tovah le'inach.
So now
the Greeks answered the precious stone is going to be the basis
for the אינך inach for the onyx and then the Romans asked
again ואינך
אינך וספר תורה. ve'inach inach vesefer Torah.
Which
one of them is going to be בסיס לחברו? basis lachavero?
Which is greater? The onyx should be the base for the Torah.
אינך לספר תורה. inach leSefer Torah.
Okay. שלחו להו
אנן ספר תורה גבן וישראל בהדן. shalchu lehu anan Sefer Torah gaban
veYisrael bahadan. So the Romans send this. If that is so, then
you need to
like להיכנע. lehikana. You need to give in to us because we
have the Torah scroll.
Sane, right? וישראל בהדן veYisrael bahadan and we have the Jewish people
with us.
So what the Romans are saying they are like the precious stone,
right, and then they carry the Jewish people which carry the Torah
on them. Okay. כפו להו. kafu lehu. The the Romans forced the
Greeks into this. עשרין ושית שנין קמו להו בהימנותא בהדי ישראל מכאן
ואילך אשתעבדו בהו. esrin veshit shanin kamu lehu beheimanuta bahadei Yisrael mikan
va'eilach ishta'abadu behu. For 26 years
the Romans and the Jewish people had this arrangement of the ruler
and the local governors but from then on they subjugated the Jews.
מעיקרא מאי דרוש ולסוף מאי דרוש מעיקרא דרוש
נסעה ונלכה ואלכה לנגדך. me'ikara mai derush ulesof mai derush me'ikara derush
nisa'ah venelechah ve'elechah lenegdecha. We're bringing two פסוקים psukim from the meet-up
between עשו Esav and יעקב Yaakov about the interactions between Rome and
the Jewish people. ולסוף דרוש יעבור נא אדוני לפני עבדו. ulesof derush
ya'avor na adoni lifnei avdo. The first one was ואלכה. ve'elechah. ואלכה
לנגדך vealcha lenegdecha we are going to go בשותפות, beshutfus, we're going
to go in partnership together with each other. But afterwards יעקב Yaakov
said יעבור נא אדוני לפני עבדו, yaavor na adoni lifnei avdo, i.e.
we will be the masters and the Romans will be the rulers.
עשרים
ושש שנים דקמו בהימנותא
בהדי ישראל מנלן? esrim
veshesh shanim dekamu beheimanuta
bahadei yisrael minalan?
How do we know 26 years?
This is just this is like would you say a very rabbinic
parable that the Greeks and the Romans would be deciding their relationship
according to seeing the Torah as the ideal?
It's so amazing also that they knew Torah, that they knew the
relationship, and some of our rabbis think, current rabbis think, yes of
course they knew the relationship between יעקב Yaakov and עשו Esav and
they knew
but of that,
yes, but I mean
what everybody's roles, because we have this Torah on
our
side and then we have
the
Romans in particular were pretty favorable towards Jews for for
in the beginning, for in the beginning.
Don't kill me but I'm going to continue until they throw us
out.
עשרים ושש שנים דקמו בהימנותא בהדי ישראל
מנלן?
esrim veshesh shanim dekamu beheimanuta bahadei
yisrael minalan?
How do we know that there's 26 years that this actually worked?
דאמר רב כהנא כשחלה רבי ישמעאל בר יוסי שלחו ליה רבי אמור
לנו שנים ושלשה דברים שאמרת לנו משום אביך. deamar Rav Kahana keshechala
Rabi Yishmael bar Yosi shalachu lei Rabi emor lanu shenayim ushlosha devarim
sheamarta lanu mishum avicha. Rav
Kahana says when רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael son of רבי יוסי Rabi
Yosi was ill, he said share with us two-three things that you
taught us from your father. אמר להו amar lehu nice teaching, רבי
ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael son of רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi is teaching אמר
להו מאה ושמונים שנה קודם שנחרב הבית פשטה מלכות הרשעה על ישראל.
amar lehu meiah ushmonim shana kodem shenecherav habayit pashta malchut harishah al
yisrael. 180 years before the destruction of the temple, Rome... whatever, trampled
Israel, right? פיי שנה עד לא חרב הבית
גזרו טומאה על ארץ העמים ועל כלי זכוכית.
pei shana ad lo
charav habayit gazru tumah al eretz haamim veal klei zechuchit.
80 years before the חורבן, churban,
the sages
decreed טומאה tumah on חוץ לארץ, chutz laaretz, that חוץ לארץ chutz
laaretz is מטמא metamei and on vessels of glass. Not going there.
ארבעים שנה עד לא חרב הבית גלתה סנהדרין וישבה לה בחנות. arbaim
shana ad lo charav habayit galta sanhedrin veyashva lah bachanot. 40 years
before the destruction of the temple the סנהדרין Sanhedrin already exiled was
exiled from לשכת הגזית lishkas hagazis and sat in a place that's
called חנות chanut in הר הבית. har habayis. למאי הלכתא? lemai hilchata?
What
why is this important halachically? אמר רב יצחק בר רב אבדימי לומר
שלא דנו דיני קנסות. amar Rav Yitzchak bar Rav Avdimi lomar shelo
danu dinei kenasos. To teach us they didn't say דיני קנסות. dinei
kenasos. Ha!
Can I? Sure.
דיני קנסות סלקא דעתך? dinei kenasos salka dachatcha? What, דיני קנסות? dinei
kenasos? Like that's not like a big deal, that's like something that
the סנהדרין Sanhedrin could do. והאמר רב יהודה אמר רב ברם זכור
אותו האיש לטוב ורבי יהודה בן בבא שמו שאילמלא הוא נשתכחו דיני
קנסות מישראל.
vehaamar Rav Yehuda amar Rav beram zachur oto haish letov veRabi Yehuda
ben Bava shemo sheilmalei hu nishtakechu dinei
kenasos miyisrael. If it was not for רבי יהודה בן בבא, Rabi
Yehuda ben Bava, then we would have forgotten the laws of fines,
of monetary punishments. נשתכחו? nishtakechu? How can you say נשתכחו? nishtakechu? Like
this is a known Torah, study from a Torah, like at Sinai.
אלא בטלו דיני קנסות מישראל כשגזרה מלכות הרשעה גזרה כל הסומך יהרג
כל הנסמך יהרג ועיר שסומכין בה תחרב ותחום שסומכין בו יתחרב.
ela batlu dinei kenasos miyisrael keshegazra malchut harishah gazra kol hasomech
yeiareg kol hanismach yeiareg veir shesomchin bah techarev utchum shesomchin bo yitacharev.
So
when Rome decreed its decree, it said everyone who teaches someone else
for rabbinic סמיכה smicha is going to be killed, everyone who is
being מוסמך musmach is going to get killed, and the city that
has סמיכה smicha is going to be destroyed, and the תחום שבת
techum shabbos that has סמיכה smicha is going to be uprooted and
I am going to let Rabbi Lenzer sadly continue with the story
of רבי יהודה בן בבא Rabi Yehuda ben Bava who is one
of the ten martyrs during the time of בר כוכבא Bar Kochba
rebellion and what he's trying to do in order to save סמיכה.
smicha. Thank you for being with us this morning and a wonderful
day.